翻译、校对： 韩非XF
请勿用于商业用途，尊重他人劳动成果
在不同时期，这里被赋予不同的名称
Across the ages it has been called many things:
边陲
The borderland,
荒野
the wild fields,
欧洲粮仓
the bread basket of Europe.
可打我从小起，乌克兰就是简单一个字：“家”
But since I was a boy, Ukraine was simply 'home'.
即使我们梦想着从俄罗斯沙皇统治下获得自由之时
Even as we dreamed of freedom from the Russian tsar,
生活还是一如既往
life went on as it always had.
不违农时
Moving to the rhythm of the seasons,
寒耕暑耘，生生不息
waxing and waning in the eternal cycle of seed, plough and reaping.
以汗水换取些许快乐的生活
A life of hard work and small pleasures.
我叫尤里·卡契尼克
My name is Yuri Kachaniuk.
耶路斯拉夫·卡契尼克的儿子
The son of Yarus/av Kachaniuk.
也是出名的战士伊万·卡契尼克的孙子
And the grandson of the famous warrior Ivan Kachaniuk.
我的乌克兰曾经是充满传奇的地方
My Ukraine was a world where legends lived.
一切皆有可能
And anything was possible.
尤里！
Yuri!
在我长大成人，以及知道巨龙真实存在
Before I grew up and earned, that dragons were real,
邪恶漫步大地以前
and evil roamed the world,
我坠入了爱河
I fell in love.
在我看见她的那一刻，我脑中一片空白
From the moment I saw her, I could think of nothing else.
我梦想长大后能娶她
I dreamed of growing up to many her,
并用一生去爱她
of loving her forever.
当布尔什维克革命浪潮向我们席卷而来时
As the Bo/shevik revolution raged its way towards us,
我的眼里只有娜塔奥卡
I could think only of Nata/ka.
就是她让你着迷的？
This is the one that's bewitched you?
你看见这口钟没有？
You see this bell?
以前是用来给村民们发出警报，当鞑靼人入侵并想征服我们
It used to warn the village when the Tartar hordes invaded, tried to conquer us,
剥夺我们自由的时候
take away our freedom.
就像沙皇那样？
Like the tsar did?
没错
Yes.
他们绝不能让你们屈服
They can never break your spirit.
没人可以！
No one!
没人可以剥夺你们的自由！
No one can ever take away your freedom!
你一定要记住这一点！
You remember that!
尤里，儿子。你来试试！
Yuri, my son. You try!
他们已经把沙皇杀了
They've killed the tsar.
- 布尔什维克吗？   - 在叶卡捷琳堡！
- The Bolsheviks?   - In Yekaterinburg!
这下乌克兰可以解放了
Now Ukraine can be free.
闹革命的已经把沙皇杀了
The revolutionaries have killed the tsar.
把军刀给他
Give him back the sabre.
他得学学如何为我们的国家而战
He needs to learn how to fight for our country,
成长为一个自由的人
grow up a free man.
他是与众不同的
He's different.
沙皇之死给乌克兰带来数年独立的光荣
The death of the tsar brought a few glorious years of independence to Ukraine.
但很快就被苏联粉碎了
But it was soon crushed by the Soviets.
大家被迫接受一种共产主义模式
The people were forced to agree to a style of communism
这项要求来自苏联领袖，列宁
that was demanded by the Soviet leader, Lenin.
还这样？现在是新的时代，尤里！
Again? It's a new age, Yuri!
宣传和鼓动是我们对国家的义务
It's our duty to the state to inform and influence,
不能光为了满足私欲
not indulge in selfish desires.
他说得对！艺术家们正涌向基辅。跟我们一起去吧！
He's right! Artists are flocking to Kiev. Come with us!
我不能走
I can't leave.
是啊...因为你正在恋爱之中
Yes... 'cause you're in love.
向她表白，然后她就能和我们一起去了
Ask her to marry you and she can come with us, too.
- 去表白吧！   - 是的...我已经...很多次了！
- Ask her!   - Yeah, I have... many times!
然后？
And?
她说我都不清楚我自己正在做什么
And she says that I don't know what I'm getting myself into.
那你就必须向她示爱。给她写诗
Then you need to woo her.
Write her a poem.
- 我可不是诗人   - 那就给她唱情歌
- I'm no poet.   - Sing her a love song.
我？唱歌？
Me? Sing?
好吧，那就，让她坐在你面前
Well, then, ask her to sit for you
让你画一幅真正的肖像
and do a real portrait,
别再光凭想像胡画一气了
instead of these fanciful doodles.
让我为你画幅画吧？
Let me paint you!
为什么？
Why?
因为你很美
Because you're beautiful.
你想在哪儿画我？
Where would you like to paint me?
在森林里吧，我们小时候一起玩的地方
In the forest, where we used to play as children.
- 哦，我明白了   - 我想把你画成水泽仙女
- Oh, I see.   - I will paint you as a rusalka.
在水边嬉戏...裸体的
Frolicking by the water... naked.
娜塔奥卡！求你，让我画吧
Natalka! Please, let me paint you.
我们说的是向她示爱！这就是你的方式？
We said woo her! Is that it?
娜塔奥卡，跟我们走吧
Natalka, come with us.
去基辅
Come to Kiev.
- 离开村子？   - 对
- Leave the village?   - Yes.
我有个叔叔，叫约瑟夫，他可以在工厂里帮尤里找份工作
I have an uncle, Josef, and he can get Yuri a job at the factory.
你一定要来
You must come.
那是我们的希望，娜塔奥卡
That's the future, Natalka.
那，是什么让你改主意的？
So, what made you change your mind?
看你当时那么绝望
You seemed so desperate.
好吧，你人在这里
Well, you are here.
这才是重点
That's all that matters.
不要有过多奢求
Don't make more of this than what it is.
不会的
Of course not.
- 我只想让你明白...   - 我不在乎
- I just need you to understand-   - I don't care.
你的父母是否结婚对我而言有何区别
What difference does it make to me whether your parents are married or not.
你觉得你不在乎，但你会的！
You think you don't, but you will!
你无法理解不被别人接受是什么感觉
You don't understand what it's like to not be accepted by others,
还有邻居们看你的眼神
judged by your neighbours.
当你能够选择的时候为什么要去找麻烦？
Why seek that trouble if you have a choice?
选择？
Choice?
- 你认为我还有选择？   - 不！别激动！
- You think I have a choice?   - No! Don't start!
不，自从我第一眼见到你开始，我就没得选择
No, I haven't had a choice about how I felt since the moment I saw you.
你明白现实吗？
Do you understand the real world?
是，我明白！
Yes I do!
我们可以共同面对
We can face it together.
你在今晚的庆典中向上帝祈祷时...你会看到的！
Tonight at the festival when you ask the gods... you'll see!
我们彼此心属对方
We belong together.
我应该嫁给他吗？
Will I ever marry'?
你不该爱上我
You shouldn't love me.
我只会给你带来不幸
I only bring you misfortune.
哦，我一直是只关心琐碎小事的傻瓜
Oh, I have been a fool for lesser things.
不要离开我，娜塔奥卡
Don't run away from me, Natalka.
嫁给我吧！
Marry me!
可是，斯大林同志，列宁同志想实行集体化
But, Comrade Stalin, Comrade Lenin tried to collectivise.
他的对象是知识分子，教堂，农民
He targeted the intelligentsia, the church, the peasants.
乌克兰人反叛了
The Ukrainians rebelled.
- 他们十分活跃！   - 列宁太仁慈了
- They flourished!   - Lenin was too lenient.
梅毒令他意志软弱
Syphilis had softened his brain.
要给乌克兰上上课来服从我们的意志
Ukraine must be taught to bow to our will.
没有那里丰富的矿产和粮食资源
Without its huge mineral wealth and vast harvests of grain,
俄罗斯就无法生存
Russia cannot exist.
那么，科巴，你觉得我们该怎么着手？
So, Koba, how do you propose we proceed?
我们贯彻列宁的计划
We implement Lenin's plan,
但不能留情
but without mercy.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
别再祷告了，牧师。我们得谈谈
Finish your prayer, priest. We need to talk.
告诉我：教堂里的金银藏在哪儿？
Tell me: Where is the churches gold and silver?
你认为那些农民需要这些东西去崇拜他们的神？
You think these peasants need all these material objects to worship their god?
挂在那儿的东西有什么价值？
And what object of value hung there?
神像在哪？
Where is the icon?
- 迪米特里！   - 是！
- Dimitri!   - Sir!
我会回来的
I will return.
同时...我建议你向你的神祷告吧
In the meantime... I suggest you pray to your god.
那对你没什么用
Not that it'll do you any good.
让你尝尝！
Take this!
他们来了
They're coming.
- 布尔什维克？   - 对
- The Bolsheviks?   - Yes.
- 敲响警钟！   - 我跟你一起去
- Sound the alarm!   - Let me come with you.
- 按你爷爷说的做   - 去，尤里，快去！
- Do as your grandfather says.   - GO, Yuri, go!
尤里，去敲警钟。快去！
Yuri, raise the alarm. GO!
我是政委谢尔盖·库佐夫
I am Commissar Sergei Koltsov.
你是博伊卡？
You are Boyko?
我能看到，博伊卡，你有一匹马...
I see, Boyko, you own a horse...
一头奶牛...
a cow...
田地
land.
你是不是雇人来种田？
Do you hire help to manage the land?
那你就是富农
Then you are kulak.
是特权阶级，国家的敌人
A privileged class, an enemy of the state.
该死的！该死的吸血鬼
Bastards! Blo0d-sucking bastards.
我只是个可怜的农民
I am a poor peasant.
这由国家来决定
That's for the state to decide.
要是肯配合，可以允许你住在合作社里
If you cooperate, you'll be allowed t0 live in the cooperative.
你是说住在我自己家？
You mean on my own land?
要是不配合，你要么会进监狱...
If you don't, you'll either be jailed...
要么枪决
or shot.
国家什么时候决定？
When will the state decide?
已经决定了
It already has.
你日落前离开
You leave at sundown.
否则，你会因擅闯国有土地被捕
If not, you'll be arrested for trespassing on state land.
你准备拿他怎么办？
What do you want with this man'?
他是国家的敌人
He's an enemy of the state.
敌人？这是胡说八道
An enemy? That's nonsense.
兄弟，你和你家人可以来我家住
Brother, you and your family are welcome to stay with us.
- 你是谁？   - 自由的人！
- And who are you?   - Free men!
追上他们！
After them!
爸爸！
Papa!
没人...没人能剥夺你的自由！
No one... no one can ever take away your freedom!
记住
Remember that.
上帝与你同在，我的孩子
God be with you, my son.
你见过那个老头吗？
Have you seen the old man?
我听说他还活着
I hear he's still alive.
别跟我撒谎，牧师！
Don't lie to my, priest!
- 这是罪过！   - 我们都是罪人
- It's a sin!   - We're all sinners.
那你有祷告吗，同志？
Then you've been praying, comrade?
- 每天都有   - 是你的上帝画了那幅神像？
- Every day.   - And has your God produced the icon?
不，不是他
No, he has not.
知道为什么吗？
Do you know why?
因为根本就没有上帝
Because there is no God.
没有邪恶，没有罪过，没有地狱
No evil, no sin, no hell.
统统都是幻想
It's all a delusion.
没有仁爱之心才是地狱！
Hell is the inability to love!
这是最后一个了
This is the last of it.
同志，我们会从明早开始建牢房
Comrade, we'll start building the cells in the morning.
够了！粮食够了
Enough! That's enough grain.
我们准备走了
We're moving out.
我爱你！出来吧我想见你！
I love you! Show yourself I want to see you!
出来吧！我想见你！
Come out! I want to see you!
- 娜塔奥卡！我的娜塔奥卡！   - 别！
- Natalka! My Natalka!   - Don't!
不，不...我爱你！跟我走吧...求你！
NO, no... I love you! Come with me... please!
塔拉斯，你喝醉了
Taras, you're drunk.
- 请你知道，我爱你！   - 别这样！
- Please! I love you!   - Stop it!
塔拉斯！她要嫁给尤里了！
Taras! She's marrying Yuri!
你去哪？
Where are you going?
我去见见朋友们，在他们去基辅之前
I'm going to see our friends before they leave for Kiev.
你的朋友都是胆小鬼
Your friends are cowards.
他们以为可以用音乐去打仗
They think they can fight battles, using music.
或是文章
And words.
尤里也很努力的
Yuri tried to help.
- 他正努力像你那样   - 他不像我！
- He's trying to be more like you.   - He's not like me!
而且一点也不像他父亲
And he's nothing like his father.
请进，来吧，尤里
Please! Come, Yuri.
我叔叔能给你找到活干
My uncle can get you work.
瞧！国家正召集艺术家
Look! The state is inviting artists.
我不能走。至少现在不行
I can't leave. Not now.
要等娜塔奥卡的妈妈身体复原
Not until Natalka's mother recovers.
我们会去的...等她好些了
We'll come... as soon as she's better.
我会尽快跟你们汇合
I'll join you as soon as I can.
再见
Good bye.
照顾好自己
Look after yourself.
除非我们能够阻止我们的经济倒退
Unless we end our economic backwardness,
否则我们西方的敌人会把我们摧毁
our enemies in the west will destroy us.
每个男人、女人和儿童都要尽责去供养工人
Every man, woman and child must do their duty to feed the workers.
粮食收入要更多地交给国家
Have the state requisition more of the harvest,
要必要的话要达到90%
up to 90% if necessary.
可是，斯大林同志，那对农民来说就相当于死刑
But, Comrade Stalin, that will be a death sentence for the farmers.
这是革命的需要！
The revolution depends on it!
想想大局吧
Think of the greater good.
也许他是对的，科巴
He's probably right, Koba.
这意味着数百万人命
This could mean the death of millions.
可谁会知道呢？
Who in the world will know?
偷盗粮食的人都已受到正义的惩罚
Those caught stealing grain have received justice.
但是这个村子的集体农庄已经失败
But the collective of this village has failed.
你们没有完成粮食限额
You did not meet your grain quota.
斯大林同志因此下令提高额度
Consequently, Comrade Stalin has ordered an increase.
整个乌克兰一视同仁。今年你们必须提高一倍产量
All over Ukraine it's the same. You must double production this year,
否则你们就有好果子吃
or you will suffer the consequences.
庄稼大部分都被天气毁掉了
Much of the harvest was lost to weather.
- 也许是被偷了？   - 你胡说！
- Or stolen?   - That's a lie!
我们没有足够的马来耕地
We don't have enough horses to plough the fields.
为什么，同志？
Why is that, comrade?
我们不得不把它们吃了！
We had to eat them!
这就是为什么斯大林同志给你们带来了拖们机
That is why Comrade Stalin brought you tractors,
机械化意味着你们必须尽责
modern mechanical means to meet your responsibilities.
而你们却通过盗窃国家财产来报答他？
And you repay him by stealing from the state?
这就是我所说的：忘恩负义
That's what I call ingratitude.
我们知道你们把粮食藏起来了
We know you're hiding grain.
签字！
Sign!
加入集体农庄
Join the collective.
会活得更好
Life will be much better.
从教堂没收的财产总值没达到我们的预期啊
Our seizure of church property has not been as lucrative as we hoped.
除去镇压外，集体化进程也很缓慢
Despite the crackdown, collectivisation is still slow.
我已经开始把富农领袖们送去西伯利亚
I've already started shipping the kulak leaders to Siberia,
但是抵抗仍很强烈，而且在蔓延
but resistance is strong and spreading.
如果不加制止，我们会失去乌克兰
If we do not stop it, we could lose Ukraine.
他们有很多想法，却不知道只有一条路可走
They think they have choices when they have only one.
逼迫他们，打击他们！
Push them, crush them!
粮食在哪？在哪？
Where is the grain? Where is it?
- 你想让我签这个字？   - 土地属于国家
- You want me to sign this?   - The land belongs t0 the state.
你，你的神像，你的田...
You, your icon, your land...
现在统统属于国家
all belong to the state now.
给，把刀拿着
Here, take the knife.
是爸爸的
It was father's.
你是时候离开了
It's time for you to leave.
在你走之前，我要你拿好
Before you leave, I want you to hold
我们村子古老而神圣的精神
the ancient and holy spirit of our village.
圣尤里的神像
The icon of Saint Yuri.
我们信念的象征
The symbol of our faith.
而这个...是父亲的梦想
And here... a father's dream.
就算我死了...他仍会活在世间
Had I gone... he would still be alive.
去基辅吧！
GO to Kiev!
去做你一直梦想的画家
GO and become the artist you've always dreamed of being.
你父亲也会如此期待
It's what your father would have wanted.
抱紧我...
Hold me...
能多久就多久！
as long as you can!
快点。上了火车我们可以想怎么做就怎么做
Come on. We can do this on the train all you like.
我不去了
I'm not coming.
什么？
What?
还没到时候
Not yet.
不，不，不...没有你我不能去
No, no, no... I can't go without you.
- 我不会...   - 你必须去！
- I won't-   - You have to!
在基辅你可以工作并把钱寄回来让我们有东西吃
In Kiev there's work for you and you can send back money so we can eat.
可离开了你，我...
To be away from you, I-
不，我...我会死的...
NO, I... I'll die...
只有妈妈好起来，我才能跟你在一起
It's just until Mother's better. Than I can be with you.
尤里！
Yuri!
基辅是你该去的地方
Kiev is where you belong.
我爱你
I love you.
这个你贴心佩戴
Wear it close to your heart.
我不认为我有那么帅
I don't think I'm that handsome.
你很有天赋
You have the gift.
谢谢
Thank you.
你这是去哪？
Where are you off to?
基辅
Kiev.
- 去工厂干活   - 用你这个特长？
- To work in a factory.   - With your talent?
- 我要为我的家尽责   - 我们都有各自的责任
- I have a duty to my family.   - We all have duties.
可你...你是个画家！
But you... are an artist!
何况你还有责任让全世界知道真相
And you have a duty to let the world know the truth,
尽你所能
an)' Way you can.
求你，求你...帮帮我！
Please, please... help me!
- 可怜可怜我吧，求你...   - 人渣！
- Have mercy on me, please...   - Scum!
- 她在讨饭吃   - 他们有食物
- She's begging for food.   - There is food.
有足够食物
Plenty of food.
党的路线就是：
That's the official party line:
没有饥荒！
No famine!
只是粮食短缺
Just a food shortage.
没有“饿死”这一说...而是，“普遍的营养不良”
No 'starvation'... instead, 'widespread malnutrition'.
我得在这儿跟你分手了
This is where I have to leave you.
- 你在做什么？停下来！   - 安静！
- What are you doing? Stop this!   - Be quiet.
你不能这么做
You can't do this.
- 你在散播西方的宣传   - 你不能这么做
- You are spreading western propaganda.   - You can't do this.
- 全世界都会听到的！   - 你跟我们来
- The whole world will hear this!   - You come with us.
把他抓起来...我们走！
Get him up... let's go!
但这是一个共同的行动来帮我们繁荣起来
But a common action to help us prosper.
我们来告知大家我们正在努力做什么
Let's educate people about what we're trying to do.
好吧，明早我们再聚
Alright, we'll reconvene in the morning.
尼古拉！
Mykola!
他终于来了！
Finally he's here!
我听到的是一个卡契尼克族人的呼唤吗？
Did I hear the call of a Kachaniuk?
- 同志，这些是用来复印的，对吗？   - 干得不错
- Comrade, these are for copying, yes?   - Excellent work.
发生了什么？你都这么成熟了
What happened? You're so grown-up.
世界都已成熟。也有我们一份
The world grew up. We're just taking part.
是时候奋起直追了，年轻人
Time for a catch-up, young man.
喝一杯吧！上帝，真好！
A drink! God, yes!
不要让党听到你说“上帝”
Don't let the party hear you say 'God'.
尤里，娜塔奥卡怎么样了？
Yuri, how is Natalka?
别让尼古拉听到...
Don't let Mykola hear...
你还爱着她吗？甚至是你那次光荣地失败之后？
Are you still in love with her? Even after you were so gracious in defeat?
没错
I was.
就让它成为我悲伤的墓志铭吧，我曾光荣地失败
Let it be my sad epitaph, I was gracious in defeat.
我们正取得进展
We're making progress.
这个城市有很多希望
There's so much hope in the city.
我们正处在国家复兴的前沿
We're On the cusp of national renaissance.
- 变化实实在在产生了   - 是啊，但怎么产生的？
- Things are really changing.   - Yes, but how?
会带来什么？
To what end?
仅就我一天之内看到的...
The things I've seen in just one day...
有些事错得离谱
something is terribly wrong.
新生事物的成长都会伴随痛苦，理所当然
Every new system has its growing pains, of course.
- 这个冬天对收成不利   - 不，比那还糟
- The winter was bad for the harvest.   - No, it's worse than that.
苏联人在我们村里，逼着我们把农田集体化
There are Soviets in our village, forcing the collectivisation of our farms.
非常极端
Violently.
而我刚一到，就看到有人在挨饿
And just arriving, I have seen people starving,
像垃圾一样自生自灭
left to rot like garbage.
我是说，你也从街上走过，肯定都看见了
I mean, you've walked the streets. You must have seen it.
现在是严重困难时期
There are severe hardships,
就像沙皇统治下一样
just as there were under the tsar.
我们现在有了属于自己的自由
We have our own freedom now,
继续前进的机会
an opportunity to push on,
重组社会，让人人享受公平待遇
to reorganise society so that everyone gets their fair share.
这是斯大林的真正理想
This is Stalin's true vision.
卡冈诺维奇...我没把你枪毙吗？
Kaganovich... haven't I had you shot?
不跟你的同志喝一杯吗？
Do you not drink with your comrades?
我带来了乌克兰的消息
I bring news from Ukraine.
我跟你说过镇压他们。为什么一次次让我失望
I told you to crush them. Why do you fail me over and over?
他们起义是因为饥饿
They rise up because they are starving.
我们的手段越残忍，他们就会反抗得更强烈
The more ruthless our methods, the more they resist.
这些该死的乌克兰人
Damn those Ukrainians.
把他们的粮食全拿走
Take all their food.
不光是粮食...所有东西！
Notjust the grain... everything!
关闭所有粮店和粮库
Close the food stores and banks.
把食品运走，关闭边境，把他们关在里面
Transport the food out. Close the borders. Keep them in.
一个也不许放
Do not let one of them leave.
别碰！
Leave it!
亲爱的尤里
Darling Yuri,
感谢你的来信，于我就像黑暗中的灯火
thank you for your letters which come to me like a beacon in the dark.
快点...
Come on...
情况越来越糟了。限额还在不断升高
Things are worse here. The quotas keep rising,
我们只能保留很少一部分收成
we get to keep less of the harvest,
越来越多的人开始饿肚子
and more and more people grow hungry.
妈妈从伤痛中得到了解脱
Mother was released from her suffering.
我好想她
I miss her so.
她一定悄悄为她的离去许了愿
She must have whispered a blessing on her journey,
尤里，因为我有一个好消息
Yuri, because I got wonderful news.
我肚子里有了我们的孩子
I'm carrying our child.
这巨大的喜悦给了我希望
This great joy gives me such hope
我可以很快去基辅见你
that I can soon join you in Kiev
能够真正听见你的声音，感受你的爱抚
and truly hear your voice and feel your touch.
我仰望明月思念着你
I look at the moon and dream of you.
也请你这么做，知道我永远是你的
Please do the same and know that I'/I always be yours.
爱你，娜塔奥卡
Love, Nata/ka.
多振奋人心的消息！
What wonderful news!
孩子！我们的孩子！
A child! Our child!
你一定要马上来基辅，这样我就能照顾你
You must now come to Kiev so I can take care of you.
我已经被学院接受了
I've been accepted into the academy,
尽管处在这么可怕的时期，我还是对我们的未来充满希望
so despite these terrible times, I have great hopes for our future.
好极了！
Perfect!
- 谢谢你   - 太好了
- Thank you.   - Too perfect.
充满了幻想
Too fanciful.
回来！
Come back!
作为一名艺术家，你必须找到真相
As an artist, you must find the truth,
而不是逃离它
not escape from it.
该怎么做？
How?
用光
With light.
只有用光你才能找到真相
With light you find the truth.
你有没有读过安德烈·布雷顿的《超现实主义宣言》？
Have you read Andre' Breton's 'Manifeste du surréalism' ?
看过萨尔瓦多·达利的作品？
Seen the works of Salvador Dali?
巴勃罗·毕加索？
Pablo Picasso?
想不想成为他们那样？
Do you dream?
对，当然想
Yes, of course.
好，那么，通过你的内心来表达你自己
Well, then, express yourself through your subconscious,
通过你的梦想
through dreams.
现实就是敌人！
Reality is the enemy!
为什么，狄多？
Why, Dido?
我不想让你为了食物而堕落
I don't want you to be forced into whoring for food.
这又能改变什么？
What difference does it make?
我们每个人都会死去！
We're all going to die!
我亲爱的，急切期待你的消息
My darling, lam desperate for news of you.
几个星期没有来信让我担心到了极点
No letters for weeks makes me fear the worst.
如果我们要接受审判，那就交给来自文明世界的成员
If we're going to be judged, then let us be judged by members of the civilised world,
而不是红色苏联帝国主义
and not by red Soviet imperialism,
交给那种斯大林不愿涉足的高级法院
to that higher court that Stalin never would want to be a part of.
乌克兰在文化方面有很多东西值得与欧洲其它国家分享
Ukraine has so much to share culturally with other countries of Europe.
那个有着达尔文，歌德的欧洲
The Europe of Darwin, of Goethe,
还有拜伦，牛顿以及，当然，马克斯
of Byron, Newton and, of course, Marx.
乌克兰可以再度骄傲
Ukrainians can be proud once again.
通过塔拉斯·舍甫琴科的文字
Inspired by the words of the great Taras Shevchenko,
通过第聂伯河的咆哮
by the roar of the Dnieper River,
通过无垠大草原的低语
the whisper of the endless steppe.
激励我们去发展我们的文化
Inspired to develop our culture
并在全世界伟大的国家中占有一席之地
and take our rightful place among the great nations of the world.
塔拉斯和我都为尼古拉感到骄傲
Taras and I are so proud of Mykola.
他已经成为乌克兰共产党的领袖
He has become leader of the Ukrainian Communist Party
以及民族运动的精神象征
and a great inspiration to the spirit of the national movement.
但我们都感觉到一些变化
But we all sense a change,
一种更黑暗，更沉重的氛围
a darker, more oppressive atmosphere.
对自由的丧失：会议，自由讨论...
A loss of freedoms: Meetings, free discussions...
甚至是旅行...一切都受到了限制
even travel... all are becoming restricted.
护照！
Passport!
这太可怕了！
It's hideous!
反动分子
Reactionary.
你必须描绘苏联振奋人心的形象！
You must paint uplifting images of the Soviet Union!
像是工厂和拖拉机？
Like factories and tractors?
你根本不是画家...
You are no artist...
- 你是国家的敌人！   - 铁木契克教授在哪？
- you are an enemy Of the state!   - Where is Professor Temchuk?
我要求跟他讲话！
I demand to speak to him!
那你就得去西伯利亚了
Then you will have to go to Siberia.
所有自我表现和个人主义都被禁止
All self-expression and individualism is being suppressed
以迎合苏联那种套路
in favour of a conformist Soviet style.
这不叫艺术
This is not art.
我被迫离开了学院
I have been forced to leave the academy
找了一份和拾荒者差不多的工作
and found work as a rag and bone man,
我们在那穿行于幽灵的纪念品之中
where we traffic in the keepsakes of ghosts,
那些因这场可怕的饥荒而逝去的人们
the ones we have lost in this terrible famine.
你在干什么！快去干活！
What are you doing! Get t0 work!
从农村来的人
The people from the countryside,
蜂涌到城里寻找食物，都在忍饥挨饿
who have flocked to the city in search of food, starve.
另外一些人，工厂里的工人，却有足够的食物
The others, the factory workers, have plenty to eat.
求求你，帮帮我们
Please, help us.
妈妈...醒一醒
Mama... wake up.
相信我，娜塔奥卡
Trust me, Nata/ka,
我不会失败的
I will not fail.
我会很快为你建好这个家
I will make it home to you soon.
乌克兰的党内要员们已经开始遭到拘捕
They've started arresting all the Ukrainian party leaders.
很快就要冲你来了
They will be with you soon.
尽可能逃吧！
Get away if you can!
我亲爱的兄弟尤里
My dear brother Yuri,
不要悲伤！
don't grieve!
你说得对
You were right.
斯大林背叛了我们所有人
Stalin has betrayed us all.
冷静！
Be calm!
我真傻，居然会相信我能够成为乌克兰爱国者和党员
I was a fool to believe I could be a Ukrainian patriot and a communist.
还傻到爱上了我最好朋友的妻子
And I was a fool to have been in love with my best friend's wife.
自我拯救吧
Save yourself,
以我做不到的方式！
like I could not!
为夜空中一闪而逝的流星
To a fire that burned brightly but was extinguished too soon.
为尼古拉，我们的朋友
To Mykola, our friend.
为尼古拉！
To Mykola!
为所有乌克兰国民
To all Ukrainian nationals.
愿他们能继续为我们节约子弹
May they continue to save us ammunition.
别让他们在我们记忆中留下污点
Don't let them spoil our memory.
为乌克兰！
To Ukraine!
为自由！
To freedom!
够了！受够那个乌克兰乡巴佬了！
Enough of that Ukrainian folk shit!
演奏《红莓花》！约瑟夫·斯大林万岁
Play Ka/inka! Long live Joseph Stalin.
- 演奏《红莓花》！   - 不，不，不，求你...
- Play Kalinka!   - NO, no, no, please-
快点！进去
Come on! In there.
快走
Keep going.
站成一排
Stay in the line.
排好队形！
Get in line!
准备！
Make ready!
瞄准！
Aim!
开火！
Fire!
站好队形！
Get in line!
谁来照顾我的家？
Who will take care of my family?
准备！
Make ready!
瞄准！
Aim!
放下枪！
Hold your fire!
尤里！
Yuri!
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
卡契尼克，我在跟你说话
Kachaniuk, I'm speaking with you.
你在墙上划什么？你打算挖洞出去？
What's that scratching? You digging your way out?
- 我在画画   - 你在画画？
- I'm drawing.   - You're drawing?
画什么？
What?
我妻子
My wife.
跪下来
On your knees.
给我画一幅
Paint me.
我需要颜料和画笔
I'll need my paints and my brushes.
以及一个回报
And a favour in return.
说说看
What?
让我给我妻子写最后一封信
Let me write a final letter to my wife.
我亲爱的
My darling,
我因谋杀入狱
I'm in prison for murder.
尼古拉死了
Mykola is dead.
我不知道他出了什么事，但感觉非常严重
I don't know what happened to Taras, but i fear the worst.
开火！
Fire!
我身边到处充满了死亡气息
There is death all around me here.
但是为了一个人而活下去的念头始终激励着我，给我希望
But having someone to live for gives me courage and hope.
我会为你活下去！
I will live for you!
还有我们的孩子！
And our child!
我相信尽我所能，我们会再相聚的
I believe with all of my being we will be together again.
- 我会跟卡契尼克在一起   - 是，长官！
- I'll be with Kachaniuk   - Yes, Sir!
那么，我什么时候能见到它？
SO, when can I see it?
稍等，快好了
Please, we're almost done.
你要保证留意了我的下颌轮廓，是我最好的特点
Make certain you capture my jawline. It's my best feature.
不，同志，是您的眼睛
No, comrade, it is your eyes.
我可不可以...
May I?
好了...
There...
是光线，让您的双眼充满神采
The light, it picks up your eyes.
让您的灵魂闪亮
It illuminates your soul.
请保持这姿势...别动
Please stay... exactly as you are.
我的眼睛是不错，不过...
My eyes are good, but...
我确实很想看看你到底画了些什么。所以...
I really must see what sort of work you've done. So...
你根本就没有灵魂
You have no soul.
有人逃了！
Escape!
娜塔莉什卡...
Natalishka...
没关系
It's alright.
这是给你的，快穿上
It's for you. Put it on.
等等
Wait.
以圣父，圣子和圣灵的名义
In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit.
我们必须拯救自己，不然就得死
We must save ourselves Or die.
很好。罗宋汤燉蘑菇，我的最爱
Yes. Borscht with mushrooms, my favourite.
- 你妈妈以前...   - 不许提她！
- Did your mother used to make-   - Never mention her!
永远都别提！
Never!
你的床上功夫和你的厨艺一样好吗？
Do you make love as well as you cook?
- 你给我下毒了   - 没有！
- You poisoned me.   - No!
- 不，政委...   - 亲我，你这个婊子！
- No, commissar-   - Kiss me, you bitch!
不要！
Don't!
妈妈！
Mama!
哦，娜塔奥卡！
Oh, Natalka!
你没事了
You're safe.
我没让家人蒙羞
I didn't dishonour the family.
给。是斯大林写的。我从政委的屋里拿到的
Here. It's written by Stalin. I took it from the commissar's headquarters.
国内已经反抗四起
There's revolts happening around the country,
但政府却保持沉默
something the regime keeps silent.
我们一定要继续抗争
We must continue the resistance.
妇女们来组织一次反抗。他们不太可能朝我们开枪
The women will organise a revolt. We'll be less likely to be shot.
- 发生什么事了？   - 为了大家的粮食！
- What's going on?   - Food for the people!
把粮食还给我们！
We want our grain!
你们想饿死我们？那就是你们想要的？
You want us to starve? Is that what you want?
别开枪！
Hold your fire!
玛利亚！玛利亚！
Maria! Maria!
玛利亚！
Maria!
伏拉迪奥...看着我
Vlodio... look at me.
你妻子被杀全都是你们的错。我真该把你们全部打死
It's your fault your wife was killed. I should have you all shot.
求你了，政委，行行好
Please, Commissar, have mercy.
- 妈妈！   - 求你了，政委
- Mother!   - Please, Commissar,
让我来埋葬她吧
let me bury her.
我不知道我的孩子们在哪
I don't know where my children are.
- 没有了玛利亚...   - 我是个有同情心的人
- Without Maria-   - I'm a compassionate man.
我会向你证明我的仁慈
I will prove to you that I am merciful
以及苏联体系的公正
and that the Soviet system is just.
我准备放了你
I will release you.
这样你就能把你妻子埋了
You can bury your wife.
但你必须向我保证你会加入集体农庄
But you must promise me you'll join the collective.
- 下地狱去吧！   - 我会看着你去
- Rot in hell!   - I'll see you there.
马可，走吧
Marko, come.
你准备拿什么来保住你家人？
What would you give to save your family?
所有东西
Everything.
除了我的灵魂
Except my soul.
给我洗脚
Wash my feet.
现在给我擦干
Now dry them.
不...
No...
用你的头发
with your hair.
擦干它们
Dry them.
把圣尤里的神像给我带来
Bring me the icon of Saint Yuri.
这样你和你家人就没事了
And you and your family will be free.
- 这是渎神！   - 不...
- This is blasphemy!   - No...
这是自由
it's freedom.
我们一直在看着你。你不是苏联人
We've been watching you. You aren't a Soviet.
- 你是谁？   - 尤里·卡契尼克
- Who are you?   - Yuri Kachaniuk.
- 你呢？   - 罗科·斯德凡涅克
- And you?   - Lubko Stefaniuk.
我们都是孤儿
We are orphans.
- 你们的村子在哪？   - 在附近，可是不安全
- Where is your village?   - Nearby, but it's not save.
你愿意帮帮我们吗？
Will you help us?
可以
Yes.
罗科，你知道火车站在哪吗？
Lubko, do you know where the train station is?
我需要到斯米拉去
I need to get to Smila.
我们是等着互相开枪呢还是吃东西？
Are we going to shoot each other or eat?
看情况吧
It depends.
- 你们是谁？   - 他们是朋友
- Who are you?   - They're friends.
你呢？
Who are you?
尤里·卡契尼克
Yuri Kachaniuk.
来自斯米拉
From Smila.
卡契尼克？
Kachaniuk?
我的爷爷是伊万
My grandfather was Ivan.
- 大野猪？   - 对
- The Wild Boar?   - Yes.
我爷爷跟他一起战斗过
My grandfather fought with him.
他突然之间冒出来挽救了他那个排。真是个传奇
He saved his platoon, appeared out of nowhere. He's a legend.
如果你是他孙子，你可以跟我们一起战斗
If you're his grandson, you can fight with us.
明天，跟本地村民一起，我们准备伏击一队苏军
Tomorrow, with the local villagers, we'll ambush a Soviet unit.
别睡着了！
Don't fall asleep!
继续前进！
Keep going!
保持阵型
Stay in formation.
我们不会给那些混蛋喘息的机会，不让他们重整队形
We'll give the bastards no breathing room, no chance to regroup.
冲啊，兄弟们！
Forward, brothers!
不！
No!
你这个傻瓜！
You fool!
尤里，醒醒！
Yuri, wake up!
我们得走了...马上！
We have to go... now!
请带上我
Please, take me with you.
我会带你上火车
I'll take you to the train.
求求你！你答应帮我的
Please! You promised to help me.
快点。火车尾巴处有一节货车箱
Come on. There's a boxcar at the end of the train.
我们在里面安全的
We'll be safe in here.
有谁能带我走？
Can somebody take me?
- 走开   - 求求你们...我的孩子！
- Get lost.   - Please... my child!
我们到了
We're here.
苏联窃贼！
Soviet thief!
尤金？
Yvgeny?
上卡车
Get in the truck.
马上
Now.
你知道你对我们的国家做了什么吗？
Do you know what you've done to our country?
- 尤里！   - 你们把一切都摧毁了
- Yuri!   - You have destroyed everything.
我当时属于红军
I was in the Red Army.
我知道乌克兰人正在挨饿，还有哈萨克人，白俄罗斯犹太人
I know Ukrainians are starving, Kazakhs, Byelorussian Jews.
但我是执行命令
But I was under orders.
- 命令？   - 尤里，别！
- Orders?   - Yuri, no!
靠边停下
Pull over.
出去
Get out.
这些粮食...
This grain...
这些够你们的人吃多久？
how long will it keep your people alive?
哪怕只能救下一条命，对我来说都够了
If I can save one life, that's enough for me.
尤里！
Yuri!
杀了他
Kill him.
他是苏联人
He's a Soviet.
他们正让我们所有人饿肚子
They're starving us all.
杀了他！
Kill him!
不！
No!
杀了他！
Kill him!
我怎么知道你不会出卖我们？
How do I know you won't turn us in?
我原本可以随时打死你们
I could have shot you at any time.
伏拉迪奥？
Vlodio?
伏拉迪奥，是我啊
Vlodio, it's me.
尤里！
Yuri!
我以为你死了
I thought you were dead.
玛利亚呢？马可呢？孩子们呢？
Maria? Marko? The children?
对不起
I'm sorry.
伏拉迪奥，我有满满一卡车的粮食
Vlodio, I have a truck full of grain.
分给大家，然后到我家来
Feed the people. Then come to my home.
我家还在吗？
Is it still there?
你还活着！
You're alive!
感谢上帝！
Thank God!
- 原谅我   - 原谅什么？
- Forgive me.   - For what?
我离开得太久了
I have been gone too long.
- 让我看看你   - 对不起
- Let me look at you.   - Sorry.
你干嘛要说对不起？
What could you possibly be sorry for'?
尤里，我们的孩子没了
Yuri, I lost our baby.
我们有自己的奇迹
We have our own miracle.
罗科！
Lubko!
他是罗科，救了我一命
This is Lubko. He saved my life.
他失去了父母
He has no parents.
现在他有我们了
He has us now.
尤里...
Yuri...
妈妈？
Mama?
是我啊...尤里
It's me... Yuri.
试着吃一小片
Try to eat a little piece.
就一点
Just a little.
吃吧
Please.
- 这是什么？   - 汤
- What is it?   - Soup.
紫蓟和草煮的
Of thistle and grass.
上帝已经原谅了我们
God has forgiven us.
他要原谅我们什么？
What could he possibly have to forgive us for?
尤里...
Yuri...
我用神像换的粮食
I traded the icon for food.
我不得不那么做
I had to.
本想救出你爷爷，但谢尔盖骗了我
To save your grandfather, but Sergei lied.
他还把他关在监狱里
He still has him prisoner.
没事的
It's okay.
我从小就一直在临摹圣尤里的神像
I have been painting icons of Saint Yuri since I was a child.
你拿去交换的...
What you traded...
只不过是其中之一
was merely one of them.
这才是真正的神像
This is the real icon.
妈妈...你看见没有？
Mama... you see?
上帝没有抛弃你
God has not forsaken you.
她安静地去了，和你父亲一道
She's at peace, with your father.
现在他们在一起了
She's with him now.
你必须把它藏好
You must hide this.
我们现在是守护者了
We are the safe keepers now.
- 我们准备带上它   - 去哪？
- We'll take it with us.   - Where?
我们要进入波兰，然后想办法去加拿大、美国
We'll cross into Poland and then make our way to Canada, America,
在那里我们可以告诉全世界，斯大林正在对乌克兰人民做什么
where we can tell the world what Stalin is doing to the people of Ukraine.
但首先我要把我爷爷救出来
But first I must free my grandfather.
等等！
Wait!
我们还留着你爷爷的军刀
We still have your grandfather's sabre.
快点！
Come on!
狄多！
Dido!
我们今晚出发，去利沃夫
We're leaving tonight, for Lviv.
原谅我吧。我真是个老糊涂
Forgive me. I'm such an old fool.
迪米特里！
Dimitri!
狄多！
Dido!
开火！别让他们逃了！
Fire! Don't let them escape!
我杀了你只是个时间问题，老家伙
It's about time I killed you, old man.
来吧，杀了我！
GO ahead! Kill me!
我孙子会为我报仇的
My grandson will have his revenge.
那个画家？
The painter?
是战士！
The warrior!
我们会得到自由
We'll be free.
有农田，和更多的孩子
Have a farm, more children.
是那条河！我们到边境了
It's the river! We're at the border.
我们马上就要进入波兰了
We'll soon be in Poland.
快点！
Come on!
- 别管我，快走！   - 不，这次不行
- Go without me!   - NO, not this time.
娜塔奥卡！快点！我们要在一起
Natalka! Come on! We'll be together.
我叫尤里·卡契尼克，是耶路斯拉夫·卡契尼克的儿子
My name is Yuri Kachaniuk, son of Yaruslav Kachaniuk,
著名战士伊万·卡契尼克的孙子
grandson of the famous warrior Ivan Kachaniuk.
在我长大成人，以及知道巨龙真实存在
Before I grew up and learned that dragons were real,
邪恶漫步大地以前
and evil roamed the world,
我坠入了爱河
I fell in love.
字幕  韩非XF